so hello everyone this is Jill brewer
the director of the Center for Applied
cultural evolution I'm sorry that I
can't join you in person but my family
is travelling today during the
conference and we're not able to come
and be with you in person and I'm really
sorry about that but I'm still delighted
and honored to have the opportunity to
share with you my vision for how the
field of cultural evolution can provide
a design science for the planetary
crisis that we're in which is related to
the need for creating economic systems
that embody the principles of living
systems that are so central to this
conference so thank you all so much for
inviting me to be here and I wish that I
could be with you in person now let me
begin by putting in context one of the
biggest patterns of the 20th century or
really of the last three centuries that
I think is really important for us to
keep in mind this graph captures it
really powerfully which is that as a set
of historical cultural changes caused
the human population to grow
exponentially starting somewhere around
the year age 100 and really taking off
in the 1940s and 1950s that the
increasing complexity of human societies
came with it a corresponding reduction
in the complexity of ecosystems all
across the planet and one way to measure
this is by looking at the rate of
extinction and you can see that as the
human population crew and we converted
more complex ecosystems into degraded
landscapes in service to agriculture and
cities and industrial processes that the
biodiversity loss going with it was
deeply coupled and that there's a very
profound relationship that needs to be
that connects the rise in human
population and social complexity with
the loss of ecological complexity seeing
an even broader view as we can through
the planetary boundaries framework
presented here that this graphic was
created by the Stockholm resilience
center which is a collaboration among
Earth System scientists where they have
identified nine key processes that they
call planetary boundaries and they've
identified that if any one of these is
crossed over a critical threshold that
it makes the possibility of a planetary
scale human civilization untenable or
said another way this threshold for the
nine different planetary boundaries
defines a safe operating range for
Humanity at a planetary scale and what
we can see by looking at this graph is
that we have already overshot several of
these planetary boundaries and we are
currently at risk of a planetary scale
system and collapse so exponential
changes that we saw in the previous
graph or represented here in things like
the loss of genetic diversity which is
up in the upper portion that's going up
to to the left which is a measure of
biodiversity loss or if you can see down
the bottom with phosphorus and nitrogen
which are connected to industrial
agriculture through the use of synthetic
fertilizers and land system change is
also rapidly moving toward the danger
zone whereas climate change even though
it's getting a lot of attention in the
press still has some time delays before
it crosses over the threshold for
planetary civilization so you can see
that in a whole system level we have
destabilized many aspects of the planet
and it's human cultural systems or the
impacts of collective human behaviors
that are called
so why isn't that the rapid changes in
human systems have had such a profound
effect on the earth overall I would
offer a very provocative idea which I
state this way
what if behavioral flexibility is the
root cause of the Earth's ecological
crisis and normally we hear things like
climate change is caused by the burning
of fossil fuels but that doesn't go deep
enough to the root causes so let's dig
into this for a moment and I'll share
with you what I mean
what is behavioral flexibility well if
you were to ask a psychologist to look
at these three different images shown
here and ask them how flexible is each
of these objects or organisms for
changing its behavior you look at a rock
which is in the bottom left and you say
well a rock can have some behavior if it
comes loose it will follow the path of
gravity and it will fall until it
settles to a new position at a lower
elevation but it is incapable of
changing its behavior by its own actions
so it has basically zero behavioral
flexibility in turtle to itself whereas
if you go to the right and say this
plant the plant has some behavioral
flexibility because if you have a light
source like if it's facing toward the
Sun on the left then the vines as
they're growing will reach in the
direction of the Sun but if you turn the
plant around the growth will move in the
opposite direction and it has a very
limited flexibility to change its
behavior in response to changing
environmental conditions but aside from
this very limited behavioral flexibility
it's still pretty limited overall and
what it can do whereas if you look at
this Mouse as laboratory mapped on the
right these animals are famous in
psychology for all of the social
experiments that can be conducted
to see how they change their behaviors
because the complex brain of a mammal
like a rodent or a lab rat is able to
learn new things from its experiences
and then change its behaviors as it
learns about new environments so this
idea of behavioral flexibility can be
thought of as a range of internal
capacities for an organism to change its
behaviors within changing environments
or to change the environment and then
adapt to the new environment by changing
its behavior now if we look at humans
what we can see is that throughout the
evolution of our ancestral line of
hominids that behavioral flexibility
increased with growing social and
technological skills so going back about
two million years ago to what is called
the Oldowan
tool age or Homo habilis back when some
of our ancestors began to use fairly
rudimentary yet at the same times quite
sophisticated tools to help them with
carving up of meat so that they could
eat it or later when they learned how to
control fire and began to cook things
that with each new step of social and
cognitive abilities came increased
behavioral flexibility which allowed our
ancestors to increasingly change their
environment to serve ourselves and so
this behavioral flexibility is a way of
thinking about how the human animal the
biological capacities of human beings
enable us to change our behaviors with
increasingly diverse repertoire and this
enables us to change which kinds of
habitats we can survive in until
eventually we became a planetary species
by adapting with technologies and
cultural adaptations to every possible
environment that humans survive in today
now add to this was very interesting
feature of cultural evolution for humans
which is that after we learn things what
we've learned becomes a kind of
structural scaffold for new innovation
and as you can see here with each later
generation of automobiles that they're
not starting from scratch each time but
instead they're taking a previous design
and all of its innovations and then
adding a few improvements and there's
accumulation of technological
innovations enables what is initially a
slow pace of change to eventually become
an exponential pace of change so the
ability for humans to change the planet
and an exponential scale is deeply
related to this cultural evolution
capacity for building upon what came
before applied at the large scale of
human history you can see it it for most
of our history roughly 99% of the
history of Homo sapiens our ancestors
lived in small tribal bands of
hunter-gatherers but when we started the
Holocene geologic period about 10,000
years ago in a few regions of the world
agriculture was developed which
substantially increased the complexity
of those societies leading to the
establishment of permanent settlements
the initial city-states growth of the
populations living within them
increasing diversity of roles and
functions that people could perform
administratively and technologically
which increased the social complexity of
those societies through a process of
cumulative cultural evolution but at the
same time this created a variety of new
social niches our new environmental
context that humans could invent new
behaviors so our capacity for behavioral
flexibility grew with this increasing
social complexity and as this process
continued to happen from generation to
generation over the span of thousands of
years
something really important occurred
which is that eventually this runaway
process of cultural evolution in human
lines created a planetary scale
civilization a planetary scale
lies economy that has destabilized earth
system functions in the 20th century so
when we looked at the planetary
boundaries framework a few minutes ago
we can see that the human capacity to
alter the entire planet was achieved
sometime in the last 100 years if not
before so if we accept the behavioral
flexibility is one of the root causes of
the Earth's ecological crisis well then
behavioral flexibility is also our only
way to avert disaster what I mean by
this is that we can use our knowledge of
how to change our behavior in ways that
embody wisdom and foresight and that
align human economic activities with the
way that ecosystems function as we're
talking about in this conference on bio
economy that we have the ability to
create cultural systems that are well
adapted to the harmony of the earth
system which means there is at least in
a theoretical sense a possibility that
we could achieve planetary
sustainability so imagine this imagine
that every location on earth where
social change occurs which is everywhere
that people are trying to make any
changes at all what if these places
became field sites for a cultural
evolution research so think about what a
field site is an anthropology a field
site is a place that a researcher goes
to study the local culture an ecology a
field site is a place where the
ecologist goes to observe different
specimens of plants animals or fungi to
see what's there but the important thing
is that the field site remains a place
of longitudinal or ongoing study to set
up baseline measurements and track
changes while also trying to understand
the mechanisms driving those changes
this rich and complex tapestry of
research tools for monitoring evaluation
analysis and
interpretation can all be used to inform
social change efforts so when I talk
about applied cultural evolution this is
what I mean that we'd take the rigor of
research and cultural evolution and
bring it to the practices of social
change so that we can address all of the
ecological and social challenges of
runaway cultural evolution that exists
in the world today so let me give a
couple examples to show that this isn't
really a new idea even though what's
been done in the past often wasn't
called applied cultural evolution you
can understand it through this lens and
a great example to start with is lista
is the field of public health so over
the last hundred hundred and fifty years
literally trillions of dollars have been
spent worldwide to eradicate disease
promote the healthy development of
children make institutions more
transparent and accountable and a lot
more so fields like prevention science
epidemiology disaster preparedness
behavioral science cultural geography
and more public policy as well these are
all areas where attempts to make social
change more rigorous and effective a lot
of areas that have a huge body of
practices and case studies that show
that it can at least within limited
capacities that it can be done
effectively similarly if we look at
education and we understand that
education is a formalized and
institutional version of something much
more general so one of the most
developed arenas for cultural evolution
research is the study of social learning
in human and non-human species so every
school on the planet in one form or
another teaches cultural narratives
social norms ideas ways of solving
problems ways of thinking developing
emotional capacities to process
information and a lot more that
changes how social learning occurs at
individual community and larger societal
scales so education in this broad way of
understanding it is an area where a huge
amount has been learned about how to
apply cultural evolution at
institutional scales another area that's
maybe a little bit more questionable in
its ethics which brings up the
importance of developing clear and
robust ethical frameworks for
participatory design is the area of
marketing so in the early days marketing
was mostly about the manipulation of
people's innate psychological capacities
in order to sell products or to build
brand identities but over time it is
very evident that marketing and
advertising have been extremely
effective at changing the pathway of
cultural evolution for entire societies
and quite honestly the entire global
economy so if we think of marketing and
advertising as areas of applied cultural
evolution we can see that there are a
lot of tools and frameworks that we can
draw upon that are effective at large
scales so now specifically applied to
bio economics we can apply things like
the capital Institute's framework for
regenerative economics which is a
synthesis of knowledge about living
systems as it's applied to how humans
might design or economic systems we now
know a great deal about the biological
organisms and ecological functions of
networks of relationships between
species and various scales from the
study of living systems when you add the
tools of complexity research and the
tools of evolution then we begin to have
the capacity to design economic systems
that have the living systems capacity to
regenerate themselves from moment to
moment and this is something that shows
great promise for the future as an area
of applied cultural evolution in my own
work I have a very specific and the
ambitious goal which is to help people
understand that if we join forces
between all of the learning centers
universities permaculture camps eco
villages transition towns and so forth
about how to guide social change that we
can direct it toward shared planetary
scale goals for example in this map you
can see all of the degraded soils on
earth and what it shows us is a target
that if we were to regenerate and end
the degradation restore the health of
all of these landscapes at a planetary
scale we can bring ourselves back within
the planetary boundaries of the
Stockholm resilience centres framework
and help to create a regenerative
economic system at a planetary scale now
part of the work that I'm doing is to
try to coordinate this through the idea
of creating bio regional scale economic
systems that organize themselves with
local learning centers that map out and
guide the evolution of their regions
while collaborating with each other from
region to region to achieve planetary
colors this is the work that we're doing
now at the Center for Applied Koechlin
evolution and we're doing it in what we
call the design Institute for
regenerating Earth which is just
beginning and has a lot of work still to
be done but the idea is to leave a
collaborative tapestry of learning
centers across the planet let's share
this vision of regenerating the entire
Earth so if this is something that
you're interested in and you'd like to
get involved well that's something I
would be very happy to talk about I like
to end on a personal note and say that
we owe it to future generations to do
the very best we can to safeguard our
collective future as a globalized
species as humanity and also for their
biodiversity of all over them
so here's a picture of me holding my
daughter who is now almost three years
old she was one year old one and a half
orange of this picture but I just wanted
to say that this is something that I
take very personally but I hold in my
heart as a sacred purpose for my own
work and building by economic systems
what can we generate the earth so if
you're interested in talking with me
about any of this or getting involved in
some way please reach out to me at this
contact information and I look forward
to talking with you at some point in the
future thank you very much